A Guide to the Carrie Johnson Papers, 1958-2005
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Carrie Johnson Papers, 1958-2005
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 199
11 boxes.
Johnson, Carolyn W. (Carrie), 1941-2018
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Carrie Johnson in 2011. Additional material donated by family members in 2018, after her death. These materials will be processed at a later time.
Biographical Information
Carolyn W. "Carrie" Johnson (1941-2018) was born in Milwaukee, WI. She graduated from Smith College in Massachusetts, and then came to the Washington, DC, area to work for centrist Republicans such as Senator Charles Mathias, Jr. (MD). In 1971, she helped advance the bill that established the Chesapeake and Ohio Canal National Historical Park. Johnson's writing work attracted the attention of Katherine Graham, owner of the Washington Post, and Graham hired Johnson to write speeches for her.
Johnson moved to Arlington in 1979 and started getting involved in her new community. She worked with the Arlington County Democratic Committee (ACDC) compiling lists of actual and potential voters, keeping the list up-to-date in a transient area. Over time, her lists became more complex and she welcomed new technology to create and maintain them. Johnson because known in ACDC circles as "The List Lady." In 2009, she won their Mary Marshall Outstanding Democrat Award.
Carrie Johnson's biggest contribution to Arlington County was her long tenure on the Planning Commission, from 1986 to 2005; Johnson was one of the longest-serving members in County history. She worked to make Smart Growth theory a reality, and was a key compromiser, able to bring disparate parties together to make a planning project a reality. Johnson was particularly proud of her work to create Long Branch Park, and was instrumental in the development of Fort Meyer Heights, Virginia Square, and Four Mile Run. After retiring from the Planning Commission, Johnson was still active in planning issues, joining working groups on projects and speaking at County Board meetings. Johnson made a vacation home in Butte, MT, and supported the local history efforts of the public libraries in both Butte and Arlington.
Scope and Content
RG 199, the Carrie Johnson Papers, is 4.6 linear feet, and dates 1958-2005, with the majority of the materials dating between 1990-2004. This collection contains Johnson's working materials for her tenure on the Planning Commission and publications that supported her work. There are memos, correspondence, meeting minutes, architectural plans, and maps, many with Johnson's handwritten notes on the margins.
These materials cover the development of several Arlington locations; this can sometimes be an entire neighborhood or just one particular building or project. It includes development of neighborhood sector plans, most notably for Virginia Square. There is significant material on Arna Valley, Pentagon Row, Rosslyn, and Virginia Square. Johnson also kept documentation on the actions and progress of the Planning Commission itself, recording its workplans and its yearly reviews. Lastly, Johnson collected publications that supported her Planning Commission efforts. Many Arlington County publications analyzed census data, and there are several publications on metro development and planning in the Washington DC area.
Arrangement
RG 199 has three series. Series 1, Projects and Planning, has materials on specific planning projects. This series has several subseries, each focused on a neighborhood or a particularly complex and large project. Some of these projects have turned into small neighborhoods themselves. Material in each subseries in generally arranged chronologically.
Series 2, Planning Commission Administration, has materials on the inner workings of the Arlington Planning Commission, and is generally arranged chronologically. Series 3, Publications, includes non-Planning Committee publications on topics related to planning and housing. This series is organized into two subseries: Arlington publications, and those published outside the county.
Folder titles in quotes (" ") reflect the original file names created by Johnson. Within quotes, anything in brackets ([ ]) were created by the archivist to clarify titles for the user. Folders with an asterisk (*) after the folder title has oversized materials that are located in special housing.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Records
RG 137, Arlington County Democratic Committee
Related Records
RG 130, Arlington County Planning Commissions Records
Index Terms
Subjects:
Arlington County Planning Commission; Arlington (Va.); Arlington County (Va.); Rosslyn (Arlington, Va.); Clarendon (Va.); Ballston (Arlington, Va.)
Contents List
- Projects and Planning
  - Rosslyn Projects and Planning
    - "Loop Road/Freedom Park," 1989, 1993 (Box 1)
    - "Courthouse Hill," 1989, 1994, 1996, 1999 (Box 1)
    - "Fort Myer Heights Background - Prospect House, Westie," 1963, 1987, 1980, 1998 (Box 1)
    - "Fort Myer Heights #1," 1991, 1998 (Box 1)
    - "Fort Myer Heights #2," 1999 (1)* (Box 1)
    - "Fort Myer Heights #2," 1999 (2)* (Box 1)
    - "Radnor Heights Projects/Monument Place, Brompton's, etc.," 1998-2001 * (Box 1)
    - "Waterview - 2000 and 2002," 1999, 2000, 2002, 2003 * (Box 1)
    - "Twin Oaks," 2000 (Box 1)
    - "1881 Nash," 2001, 2004 * (Box 2)
    - "Navy League," 2001 * (Box 2)
    - "Odyssey," 2001 (Box 2)
    - "WRIT Site Plan," 2002 * (Box 2)
    - "1800 Wilson," 2003 * (Box 2)
    - "Woodbury Park," 2003 * (Box 2)
    - "Rosslyn Ridge - 1," 2003 (1) (Box 2)
    - "Rosslyn Ridge - 1," 2003 (2)* (Box 2)
    - "Gables-Troy St.," 2004 * (Box 2)
    - "Rosslyn Ridge - 2," 2004 (1) (Box 3)
    - "Rosslyn Ridge - 2," 2004 (2) (Box 3)
    - "Rosslyn Ridge #3/6-04 PC/CB," 2004 * (Box 3)
    - "Quality Inn (CH Road/50)," 2005 * (Box 3)
    - "Rosslyn Transportation 1991-1996," 1991, 1994 (Box 3)
    - "In-Between Study, Rosslyn-Courthouse," 2001-2003 (Box 3)
    - "Rosslyn C-O District 1996+," 1996, 1997, 2001, 2002 (1) (Box 3)
    - "Rosslyn C-O District 1996+," 1996, 1997, 2001, 2002 (2) (Box 3)
    - "Rosslyn Heights and Tapering," 2002 (Box 3)
  - Courthous Projects and Planning
    - "Courthouse Area - 90s," 1988, 1997 (Box 3)
    - "[Courthouse] Sector Plan Addendum," 1993 (Box 3)
  - Clarendon Projects and Planning
    - "Clarendon Projects - The Hudson," 2000 (Box 4)
    - "Clarendon Projects - Post Office Block," 2003 * (Box 4)
    - "BF Saul - Clarendon Center," 2004 * (Box 4)
    - "Clarendon Projects - Peete - Fillmore Street," 2004 * (Box 4)
    - "Clarendon Projects - Garfield Park," 2004 * (Box 4)
    - "Clarendon Projects - 1201 N. Irving," 2005 * (Box 4)
    - "Clarendon Plans and Studies," 2001, 2003 (Box 4)
    - Clarendon Sector Plan Work, 1982-1994 (1) (Box 4)
    - Clarendon Sector Plan Work, 1982-1994 (2) (Box 4)
  - Virginia Square Projects and Planning
    - "VA [Square] Apartments," 1999-2000 (1) (Box 5)
    - "VA [Square] Apartments," 1999-2000 (2) (Box 5)
    - "VA [Square] Apartments," 1999-2000 (3) (Box 5)
    - "VA Square Projects - 3409 Wilson, Monroe St. Condos," 2003 * (Box 5)
    - 3409 Wilson Boulevard, 2003 * (Box 5)
    - Virginia Square Sector Plan, 1986, 1992, 2002 (1) (Box 5)
    - Virginia Square Sector Plan, 1986, 1992, 2002 (2)* (Box 5)
    - Virginia Square Sector Plan Development, 1990, 1994, 2000, 2001 (Box 5)
    - "Virginia Square, 2002 - #2" Sector Plan, 2002 (Box 6)
    - "VA Square GLUP and Zoning Amendments," 2003 (Box 6)
  - Ballston Projects and Planning
    - "Ballston Projects, Mid-1990s," 1983, 1994, 1996-1997 (1) (Box 6)
    - "Ballston Projects, Mid-1990s," 1983, 1994, 1996-1997 (2) (Box 6)
    - "Quincy St. Extension," 1990-1992 (Box 6)
    - "Quincy St. Extension," 1994-1996, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Rosslyn-Ballston Corridor Projects and Planning
    - "Mall Axis 1982," 1982 (Box 6)
    - "R-B Corridor Mid-Course Review," 1984, 1988-1990 (Box 6)
  - East Falls Church Projects and Planning
    - "East Falls Church Planning 1986-2004," 1986, 1987, 1998, 1999, 2003, 2004 (1)* (Box 6)
    - "East Falls Church Planning 1986-2004," 1986, 1987, 1998, 1999, 2003, 2004 (2)* (Box 7)
  - Pentagon Town Center/Pentagon Row Projects and Planning
    - Pentagon Town Center/Pentagon Row, October-December 1997 * (Box 7)
    - Pentagon Town Center/Pentagon Row, 1997-1998 (1) (Box 7)
    - Pentagon Town Center/Pentagon Row, 1997-1998 (2) (Box 7)
    - Pentagon Town Center/Pentagon Row, August-November 1997 (1) (Box 7)
    - Pentagon Town Center/Pentagon Row, August-November 1997 (2) (Box 7)
    - Pentagon Town Center/Pentagon Row, 1955, 1958, 1959, 1972, 1990, 1997 (1) (Box 8)
    - Pentagon Town Center/Pentagon Row, 1955, 1958, 1959, 1972, 1990, 1997 (2) (Box 8)
  - Arna Valley Projects and Planning
    - "Arna Valley Ap[artments] #1," 1991, August-November 1998 (Box 8)
    - "Arna Valley Apartments #2," September-December 1998 (Box 8)
    - "Arna Valley Apartments #3," November 1998 (Box 8)
    - "Arna Valley Ap[artmen]ts #4," 1996, 1998, n.d. (1) (Box 8)
    - "Arna Valley Ap[artmen]ts #4," 1996, 1998, n.d. (2) (Box 8)
    - Arna Valley, 1998-1999, n.d.* (Box 8)
  - Potomac Palisades Projects and Planning
    - Potomac Palisades Development, 1958-1989, n.d. (1) (Box 9)
    - Potomac Palisades Development, 1958-1989, n.d. (2) (Box 9)
    - Potomac Palisades Task Force, 1987, 1989-1990, n.d. (Box 9)
- Planning Commission Administration
  - "SPRC Policies and Review," 1989, 1991, 1994-1997 (Box 9)
  - "Planning - Laws and Processes and General Co. Standards," 1987, 1988, 1991, 1994, 1995 (1) (Box 9)
  - "Planning - Laws and Processes and General Co. Standards," 1987, 1988, 1991, 1994, 1995 (2) (Box 9)
  - Completed Site Plan Projects, 1996, 2000 (Box 9)
  - Planning Commission Yearly Reviews, 2001, 2002 (Box 9)
  - "Comprehensive Plan Reviews - Work Plan 2000+," 2000-2002, n.d. (Box 9)
- Publications
  - Arlington County Publications
    - Rosslyn-Ballston Corridor Development Publications, 1972, 1975, 1976, 2002 (Box 10)
    - "A Long-Range County Improvement Program," 1975 (Box 10)
    - County Manager Regulation on Public Recreational Facilities, 1982 (Box 10)
    - Arlington "Offering Circular" Bond Sale, 1985 (Box 10)
    - "Arlington Virginia Profile," 1985, 1986, 1996, 2001 (Box 10)
    - Arlington "Community, Citizens, Civic, and Service Organizations," 1986 (Box 10)
    - Historic Maywood Publications, 1987, 1990, 1991 (Box 10)
    - Metro Corridor Development Publications, 1990, 2000, 2004 (Box 10)
    - Arlington County Census Data Reports, 1991, 1992, 1995, 1996, 2002 (Box 10)
    - Planning Information Reports, 1991, 1992, 1994, 1995, 1998, 2002, 2004 (Box 10)
    - "Arlington Trends," 1992 (Box 10)
    - Metro Station Area Profile/Demographics," 1994, 2003 (Box 10)
    - "Vision 2020," 1995 (Box 10)
    - "Preserving Economic Growth and Quality of Life in Arlington," 1995 (Box 11)
    - "Mapping the Arlington Way," 2000 (Box 11)
    - Arlington Economic Development Publications, 2003, n.d. (Box 11)
    - Arlington Forum Publications, 2003, 2006 (Box 11)
    - "Virginia Square Sector Plan, November 2002," 2002 (Box 11)
    - "Arlington County in Perspective," 2004 (Box 11)
  - Non-Arlington Publications
    - "Toward a New Dominion: Choices for Virginians," 1984 (Box 11)
    - Metro Washington Council of Governments Publications, 1989, 1991, 1992, 1995 (Box 11)
    - "Transit Oriented Development Best Practices Manual," 2002 (Box 11)
    - Small Business Ombudsman Update, EPA, July 2002 (Box 11)
    - "Built Environment - Healthy Communities, Healthy Homes, Healthy People," 2002 (Box 11)
    - Ad Hoc Baseball Stadium Advisory Committee, 2003* (Box 11)